{
  "reference_number": "11607",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I support a 2050 target, but believe the majority of the emission cuts should be achieved in a shorter period - aiming for 2040. New\n Zealand has a poor, historical record with regards to emissions and needs to make every effort to achieve this goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I also support taking a science-based approach to ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as impactful as possible: we should\n\n aim for negative levels of long-lived gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels. However, the period should be\n shortened - cuts should be achieved in a shorter period - aiming for 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I support the ‘firewall’ principle, that New Zealand’s emission reduction targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own\n\n emissions, and not through the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only in a more ambitious direction and under stated provisions, such as scientific advances, changes in international law or\n unforeseen climate changes (tipping points reached). Any revision should require input from the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with 5-year budgets set 10-15 years in advance, so that 3 are in effect at all times. However, New Zealand should adopt the\n\n most progressive budget regime possible. There is no time to waste."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The third emissions budget should only be able to be changed if required to achieve the goal of Zero Carbon by 2050, or, preferably\n 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Emissions budgets should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines their long-term certainty. However,\n\nthe ability to revise budgets in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements should be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should include the following factors when advising on and setting budgets:\n\n• scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • global leadership, including international\nequity"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Act must require the Government to set and public plans to stay within budget as rapidly as feasible, within a set\ntime limit that is certainly less than 12 months."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Time is of the essence. The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair and just, cost-\n\neffective, environmentally sustainable and reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Commission should not be a decision-making body. However, the Government should be legally required to consider and\nformally respond to the Commission’s advice, and to provide an explanation if they do not act on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "It should not be the role of the CCC to make decisions on the number of units available."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\nimpacts (including environmental, social, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\n\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges such\nas planning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development\nsystems."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government needs to prepare a national climate risk assessment and produce an adaptation programme to address any\nidentified risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\n\nadaptation plan"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A targeted adaptation reporting power could start with voluntary reporting in the first year, that could be shared, and require\ncompulsory reporting in subsequent years."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There needs to be more emphasis on the effects on the natural environment and biodiversity, and how any further adverse effects\ncan be avoided."
    }
  ]
}
